<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pol Castellano on Pol Castellano</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pol Castellano on Pol Castellano</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Pol Castellano</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>FOBI: An ontology to represent food intake data and associate it with metabolomic data</title>
      <link>/talk/fobi_bioinformatics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/fobi_bioinformatics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nutrition research can be conducted by using two complementary approaches: 1) traditional self-reporting methods or 2) via metabolomics techniques to analyze food intake biomarkers in biofluids. However, the complexity and heterogeneity of these two very different types of data often hinder their analysis and integration. To manage this challenge, we have developed a novel ontology that describes food and their associated metabolite entities in a hierarchical way. This ontology uses a formal naming system, category definitions, properties and relations between both types of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ontology presented is called FOBI (Food-Biomarker Ontology) and it is composed of two interconnected sub-ontologies. One is a ”Food Ontology” consisting of raw foods and prepared foods while the second is a ”Biomarker Ontology” containing food intake biomarkers classified by their chemical classes. These two sub-ontologies are conceptually independent but interconnected by different properties. This allows data and information regarding foods and food biomarkers to be visualized in a bidirectional way, going from metabolomics to nutritional data or vice versa. Potential applications of this ontology include the annotation of foods and biomarkers using a well-defined and consistent nomenclature, the standardized reporting of metabolomics workflows (e.g. metabolite identification, experimental design), or the application of different enrichment analysis approaches to analyze nutrimetabolomic data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>POMA: Shiny Framework Statistical analysis tool for targeted metabolomic data</title>
      <link>/talk/poma_user2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/poma_user2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Similarly to other high-throughput technologies, metabolomics usually faces a data mining challenge to provide an understandable and useful output to advance in biomarker discovery and precision medicine. Biological interpretation of the results is one of the hard points and several bioinformatics tools have emerged to simplify and improve this step. However, sometimes these tools accept only very simplistic data structures and, for example, they do not even accept data with several covariates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POMA is a free, friendly and fast Shiny interface for analysing and visualization data after an analytical targeted metabolomics process and its hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://polcastellano.shinyapps.io/POMA/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://polcastellano.shinyapps.io/POMA/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POMA allows the user to go from the raw data to statistical analysis. The analysis is organized in three blocks: “Load Data” (where user can upload metabolite data and a covariates file), “Pre-processing” (value imputation and normalization) and “Statistical analysis” (univariate and multivariate methods, limma, correlation analysis, feature selection methods, random forest, etc.). These steps include multiple types of interactive data visualization integrated in an intuitive user interface that requires no programming skills. Finally, POMA also generates different automatic statistical and exploratory reports to facilitate the analysis and interpretation of the results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogdown: Make your own website easily with R!</title>
      <link>/post/blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/blogdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pcastellanoescuder/blogdown_slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Go to slides repository!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>POMA: Shiny Framework Statistical analysis tool for targeted metabolomic data</title>
      <link>/talk/poma-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/poma-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Similarly to other high-throughput technologies, metabolomics usually faces a data mining challenge to provide an understandable and useful output to advance in biomarker discovery and precision medicine. Biological interpretation of the results is one of the hard points and several bioinformatics tools have emerged to simplify and improve this step. However, sometimes these tools accept only very simplistic data structures and, for example, they do not even accept data with several covariates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POMA is a free, friendly and fast Shiny interface for analysing and visualization data after an analytical targeted metabolomics process and its hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://polcastellano.shinyapps.io/POMA/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://polcastellano.shinyapps.io/POMA/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POMA allows the user to go from the raw data to statistical analysis. The analysis is organized in three blocks: “Load Data” (where user can upload metabolite data and a covariates file), “Pre-processing” (value imputation and normalization) and “Statistical analysis” (univariate and multivariate methods, limma, correlation analysis, feature selection methods, random forest, etc.). These steps include multiple types of interactive data visualization integrated in an intuitive user interface that requires no programming skills. Finally, POMA also generates different automatic statistical and exploratory reports to facilitate the analysis and interpretation of the results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>POMA</title>
      <link>/project/poma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/poma/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;poma-statistical-analysis-tool-for-targeted-metabolomic-data&#34;&gt;POMA: Statistical analysis tool for targeted metabolomic data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f49338&#34;&gt;Fast:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Analyze and visualize your data in few steps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f49338&#34;&gt;Friendly:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; POMA is very intuitive and no needed programming skills in any step of workflow&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f49338&#34;&gt;Free:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; All POMA options and analysis are completely free for all users&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;input-data&#34;&gt;Input Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload your data in the &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Input Data&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; tab.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data must be a .CSV &lt;em&gt;comma-separated-value&lt;/em&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First/Left-hand column must be sample IDs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second/Left-hand column must be sample groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally, first row should be column names (metabolites).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metabolomic Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each row denotes a sample and each column denotes a metabolite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/met_data.png&#34; alt=&#34;Metabolites&#34; title=&#34;Metabolomic Data&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;250&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covariates file (optional)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each row denotes a sample (the same as in metabolomic data) and each column denotes covariate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/cov_data.png&#34; alt=&#34;Covariates&#34; title=&#34;Covariates File&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;impute-values&#34;&gt;Impute Values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metabolomics data usually presents a high number of missing values. By default, the missing values are treated as the result of low signal intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, the imputation of missing values is an essential step in metabolomic data analysis workflow. To deal with that, POMA provides the &lt;strong&gt;Impute Value&lt;/strong&gt; panel which allows the user:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To remove all metabolites of the data that have more of specific percentage (defined by user) of missing values in ALL study groups. By default this parameter is 20%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To impute missing values of the data using different methods such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replace by zero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replace by half of the minimum positive value in the original data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replace by median&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replace by mean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replace by minimum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KNN method (default)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;normalization&#34;&gt;Normalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normalization is required to make all metabolites comparable among them. By default the application do not normalize data, however it is recommended to select one normalization method. POMA app offers all these following different types of normalization methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autoscaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vast scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log Pareto scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;statistics&#34;&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statistical Analysis tab contains a set of different panels to analyze the data:  1) Univariate analysis; 2) Multivariate analysis; 3) Limma; 4) Correlation analysis; 5) Random Forest; 6) Feature selection and 7) Rank Products. Each one of them includes different options and methods. Below is a brief explanation of each one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;univariate-analysis&#34;&gt;Univariate analysis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Univariate Analysis panel contains five types of analysis to perform comparaisions of each group per each metabolite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;u-parametric-tests-u&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Parametric tests&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;T-test: The results can be shown with an interactive &lt;strong&gt;volcano plot&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/volcano.png&#34; alt=&#34;VOLCANO&#34; title=&#34;VOLCANO PLOT&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One-way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA): If data has a normal distribution and more than two groups.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;All of the previous methods can be corrected by covariables if the user has provided a covariate matrix.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;u-non-parametric-tests-u&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Non-Parametric tests&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mann-Whitney U Test: If data has two groups and non-normal distribution. If data is paired, this test becomes to Wilcoxon Signed Rank Test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kruskal Wallis Test: If data has a non-normal distribution but more than two groups.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;multivariate-analysis&#34;&gt;Multivariate analysis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step is powered by &lt;strong&gt;mixOmics R package&lt;/strong&gt;. POMA multivariate analysis includes three principal multivariate methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principal Component Analysis (PCA)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/pca.png&#34; alt=&#34;PCA&#34; title=&#34;PCA&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partial Least Squares Discriminant Analysis (PLS-DA)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/plsda.png&#34; alt=&#34;PLSDA&#34; title=&#34;PLSDA&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;pix/plsda_errors.png&#34; alt=&#34;PLSDAERR&#34; title=&#34;PLSDA ERRORS&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sparse Partial Least Squares Discriminant Analysis (sPLS-DA)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/splsda.png&#34; alt=&#34;SPLSDA&#34; title=&#34;SPLSDA&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;limma&#34;&gt;Limma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;linear models for microarray and RNA-Seq Data&lt;/em&gt;. This function is implemented in limma R package and is prepared to perform a singl-sample t-test using an empirical Bayes method to borrow information between metabolites. The final output is a list of metabolites with a column with a value of the contract (logFC). The AveExpr column gives the average log2-expression level for that gene across all the arrays and channels in the experiment. Column t is the moderated t-statistic. Column P.Value is the associated p-value and adj.P.Value is the p-value adjusted for multiple testing by false discovery rate (FDR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;correlation-analysis&#34;&gt;Correlation analysis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Correlation analysis tab includes two different ways to visualize the correlations in your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pairwise Correlation Scatterplot: This scatterplot show the correlation (and p-value of this correlation) between two metabolites in the data. The user can choose any pair of metabolites in the dataset and modify the correlation method (pearson, spearman or kendall) in a reactive, fast and easy panel.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/correlations.png&#34; alt=&#34;CORR&#34; title=&#34;CORRELATIONS&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global Correlation Heatmap: Where you can see the correlation matrix of your data in a heatmap format. This plot show all correlations in data at the same time.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/global_correlations.png&#34; alt=&#34;GCORR&#34; title=&#34;GLOBAL CORRELATIONS&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;random-forest&#34;&gt;Random Forest&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random forests or random decision forests are an ensemble learning method for classification, regression and other tasks that operates by constructing a multitude of decision trees. This methods are included in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;machine learning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POMA includes a Random Forest algorithm for group classification based on &lt;strong&gt;caret&lt;/strong&gt; R package. POMA interface allows user to tune all the Random Forest parameters in a easy way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/random_forest.png&#34; alt=&#34;RANDOMFOR&#34; title=&#34;RANDOM FOREST&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;feature-selection&#34;&gt;Feature Selection&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In statistics, feature selection, also known as variable selection, is the process of selecting a subset of relevant features (for example, metabolites) for use in model construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POMA includes a section thought specified for feature selection. This section includes two of the most used methods for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ridge regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lasso
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/lasso.png&#34; alt=&#34;LASSO&#34; title=&#34;LASSO&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rank-products&#34;&gt;Rank Products&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rank product is a biologically motivated test for the detection of differential features in high throughput experiments. It is a simple &lt;strong&gt;non-parametric&lt;/strong&gt; statistical method based on ranks of fold changes. It can be used to combine ranked lists in various application domains, including proteomics, statistical meta-analysis and general feature selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pix/rankprod.png&#34; alt=&#34;RANKPROD&#34; title=&#34;RANK PRODUCTS&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;230&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenome-wide association study in Childhood Obesity: Searching for early markers of late disease risk</title>
      <link>/talk/epimet-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/epimet-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale&lt;/strong&gt;: Childhood obesity is one a major Public Health
issue. Overweight/obese children have a high risk of being
obese as adults and develop other co-morbidities, including type
2 diabetes, cardiovascular disease and several types of cancer.
It has been proposed that epigenetic mechanisms might be
involved in mediating long-term metabolic dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: Here we analyzed DNA methylation profiles (Infinium
MethylationEPIC BeadChip, 850K) in whole blood from 26
obese (zBMI &amp;gt; 2) and 12 control lean pre-pubertal children
(zBMI &amp;lt; 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;:109 CpG sites appeared differentially methylated
between the two groups (methylation change 10% and FDR
value &amp;lt;0.05). 5 out of the 109 targets, were located within the
SPATC1L (Spermatogenesis and Centriole Associated 1 Like)
gene. Next, we performed a Two Sample Mendelian
Randomization test, and found that 2 of the 5 CpG sites
mapping the SPATC1L locus are causal for multiple disorders,
including childhood obesity, type 2 diabetes, ulcerative colitis
and inflammatory bowel disease. SPATC1L expression was
similar in whole blood of obese and lean subjects. However, the
contiguous genes COL6A2 and COL6A3 (Collagen Type VI
Alpha 2 and 3 Chains), which are strongly associated to obesity,
were differentially expressed between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion&lt;/strong&gt;: Childhood obesity is associated to a small change
in DNA methylation (109 CpG sites). In our dataset, only 2 CpG
sites appeared to play a causative role in the development of
the disease. We hypothesize that these CpG sites might
mediate disease risk by modulating the expression of physically
close genes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FBOnto: An ontology to represent food intake data and associate it with metabolomic data</title>
      <link>/talk/fbonto_bio-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/fbonto_bio-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Currently, nutrition research generates a lot of complex data hard to analyze and associate with other data or omics such as metabolomics. By itself, metabolomics is closely linked to nutrition. However, it is still difficult to associate these two types of data. One reason for this difficulty is the heterogeneity found in the information provided by participants in nutritional studies about what they have eaten. In order to
manage this heterogeneity we have decide to build an ontology, describing foods in a
hierarchichal way that enables a common description of food intake. This ontology
contains formal naming, definition of the categories, properties, and relations
between the concepts of two types of data, food and related metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ontology has been created using Protégé 5.2.0 version. As is common in
ontologies, FBOnto (Food-Biomarker Ontology) has been written in OWL language (Web
Ontology Language).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ontology presented is called FBOnto and is made of two sub-ontologies. The first
ontology describes foods: from simple such as fruits and vegetables to more complex
foods such as ratatouille. The second ontology describes metabolites, grouped in their
different chemical classes. The nodes or elements of these two sub-ontologies are
connected by the properties of each one, so that if a metabolite is in different foods, it
will connect with all of them. This ontology allows us to visualize data in a
bidirectional way, going from metabolomics to nutritional data or vice versa. In
addition, this ontology can also be useful for other analyses such as enrichment analysis
or a novel concept, food-enrichment analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifestyle intervention decreases urine trimethylamine N-oxide levels in prepubertal children with obesity</title>
      <link>/publication/obesity_carles_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/obesity_carles_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt; Early lifestyle interventions in children with obesity decrease risk of future obesity
and metabolic disorders. However, the metabolic effects of such interventions are not
completely characterized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; We analyzed the impact of lifestyle intervention in the urine metabolome from
prepubertal children. We studied 34 prepubertal children with obesity before and after a 6-
month-long lifestyle intervention program. We applied a nuclear magnetic resonance approach
to obtain the metabolomic profile from urine samples. Partial Least Squares-Discriminant
Analysis (PLS-DA) was used to achieve group classification and variable importance on
projection (VIP) for biomarker selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; The intervention reduced caloric intake by 10% (p&amp;lt;0.05) and BMI-SDS by 0.47 SD
(p&amp;lt;0.001). PLS-DA identified trimethylamine N-oxide (TMAO, VIP=2.21) as the metabolite with
the highest discrimination properties between groups. Urine TMAO levels were reduced after
the intervention (p&amp;lt;0.05). TMAO is a biomarker of cardiovascular disease risk and is a product
of gut microbiota-dependent metabolism of certain dietary compounds, including choline.
Notably, changes in TMAO levels after the intervention did not correlate to differences in choline
intake but were inversely associated with fiber intake (p&amp;lt;0.05).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; Our results indicate that TMAO levels are decreased by lifestyle intervention in
children with obesity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenome-wide association study in childhood obesity</title>
      <link>/talk/metnet-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/metnet-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Childhood obesity is one a major Public Health issue. Overweight/obese children have a
high risk of being obese as adults and develop other co-morbidities, including type 2
diabetes, cardiovascular disease and several types of cancer. It has been proposed that
epigenetic mechanisms might be involved in mediating long-term metabolic
dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we analyzed DNA methylation profiles (Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip
850K) in whole blood from 26 obese (zBMI &amp;gt; 2) and 12 control lean pre-pubertal
children (zBMI &amp;lt; 1). 109 CpG sites appeared differentially methylated between the two
groups (methylation change &amp;gt;10% and FDR value &amp;lt;0.05). 5 out of the 109 targets, were
located within the SPATC1L (Spermatogenesis and Centriole Associated 1 Like) gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we performed a Two Sample Mendelian Randomization test, which allows
determining whether a particular CpG site is causal or consequence for the disease.
Strikingly, we found that 2 of the 5 CpG sites mapping the SPATC1L locus are causal for
multiple disorders, including not only childhood obesity, but also type 2
diabetes, ulcerative colitis and inflammatory bowel disease. SPATC1L expression was
similar in whole blood of obese and lean subjects. However, the contiguous
genes COL6A2 (Collagen Type VI Alpha 2 Chain), LSS (Lanosterol Synthase), YBEY (YbeY
Metallopeptidase) and C21orf58 were differentially expressed between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, we show that childhood obesity is associated to a small change in DNA
methylation (109 CpG sites). In our dataset, only 2 CpG sites appeared to play a
causative role in the development of the disease. We hypothesize that these CpG sites
might mediate disease risk by modulating the expression of physically close genes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenome-wide association study in childhood obesity</title>
      <link>/talk/bioinformatics-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/bioinformatics-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Childhood obesity is one a major Public Health issue. Overweight/obese children have a
high risk of being obese as adults and develop other co-morbidities, including type 2
diabetes, cardiovascular disease and several types of cancer. It has been proposed that
epigenetic mechanisms might be involved in mediating long-term metabolic
dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we analyzed DNA methylation profiles (Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip
850K) in whole blood from 26 obese (zBMI &amp;gt; 2) and 12 control lean pre-pubertal
children (zBMI &amp;lt; 1). 109 CpG sites appeared differentially methylated between the two
groups (methylation change &amp;gt;10% and FDR value &amp;lt;0.05). 5 out of the 109 targets, were
located within the SPATC1L (Spermatogenesis and Centriole Associated 1 Like) gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we performed a Two Sample Mendelian Randomization test, which allows
determining whether a particular CpG site is causal or consequence for the disease.
Strikingly, we found that 2 of the 5 CpG sites mapping the SPATC1L locus are causal for
multiple disorders, including not only childhood obesity, but also type 2
diabetes, ulcerative colitis and inflammatory bowel disease. SPATC1L expression was
similar in whole blood of obese and lean subjects. However, the contiguous
genes COL6A2 (Collagen Type VI Alpha 2 Chain), LSS (Lanosterol Synthase), YBEY (YbeY
Metallopeptidase) and C21orf58 were differentially expressed between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, we show that childhood obesity is associated to a small change in DNA
methylation (109 CpG sites). In our dataset, only 2 CpG sites appeared to play a
causative role in the development of the disease. We hypothesize that these CpG sites
might mediate disease risk by modulating the expression of physically close genes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenome-wide association study in childhood obesity</title>
      <link>/talk/febs3-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/febs3-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Childhood obesity is one a major Public Health issue. Overweight/obese children have a
high risk of being obese as adults and develop other co-morbidities, including type 2
diabetes, cardiovascular disease and several types of cancer. It has been proposed that
epigenetic mechanisms might be involved in mediating long-term metabolic
dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we analyzed DNA methylation profiles (Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip
850K) in whole blood from 26 obese (zBMI &amp;gt; 2) and 12 control lean pre-pubertal
children (zBMI &amp;lt; 1). 109 CpG sites appeared differentially methylated between the two
groups (methylation change &amp;gt;10% and FDR value &amp;lt;0.05). 5 out of the 109 targets, were
located within the SPATC1L (Spermatogenesis and Centriole Associated 1 Like) gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we performed a Two Sample Mendelian Randomization test, which allows
determining whether a particular CpG site is causal or consequence for the disease.
Strikingly, we found that 2 of the 5 CpG sites mapping the SPATC1L locus are causal for
multiple disorders, including not only childhood obesity, but also type 2
diabetes, ulcerative colitis and inflammatory bowel disease. SPATC1L expression was
similar in whole blood of obese and lean subjects. However, the contiguous
genes COL6A2 (Collagen Type VI Alpha 2 Chain), LSS (Lanosterol Synthase), YBEY (YbeY
Metallopeptidase) and C21orf58 were differentially expressed between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, we show that childhood obesity is associated to a small change in DNA
methylation (109 CpG sites). In our dataset, only 2 CpG sites appeared to play a
causative role in the development of the disease. We hypothesize that these CpG sites
might mediate disease risk by modulating the expression of physically close genes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
