<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Josep Jiménez-Chillarón | Pol Castellano</title>
    <link>/author/josep-jimenez-chillaron/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/josep-jimenez-chillaron/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Josep Jiménez-Chillarón</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Pol Castellano</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Josep Jiménez-Chillarón</title>
      <link>/author/josep-jimenez-chillaron/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifestyle intervention decreases urine trimethylamine N-oxide levels in prepubertal children with obesity</title>
      <link>/publication/obesity_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/obesity_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt; Early lifestyle interventions in children with obesity decrease risk of future obesity
and metabolic disorders. However, the metabolic effects of such interventions are not
completely characterized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; We analyzed the impact of lifestyle intervention in the urine metabolome from
prepubertal children. We studied 34 prepubertal children with obesity before and after a 6-
month-long lifestyle intervention program. We applied a nuclear magnetic resonance approach
to obtain the metabolomic profile from urine samples. Partial Least Squares-Discriminant
Analysis (PLS-DA) was used to achieve group classification and variable importance on
projection (VIP) for biomarker selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; The intervention reduced caloric intake by 10% (p&amp;lt;0.05) and BMI-SDS by 0.47 SD
(p&amp;lt;0.001). PLS-DA identified trimethylamine N-oxide (TMAO, VIP=2.21) as the metabolite with
the highest discrimination properties between groups. Urine TMAO levels were reduced after
the intervention (p&amp;lt;0.05). TMAO is a biomarker of cardiovascular disease risk and is a product
of gut microbiota-dependent metabolism of certain dietary compounds, including choline.
Notably, changes in TMAO levels after the intervention did not correlate to differences in choline
intake but were inversely associated with fiber intake (p&amp;lt;0.05).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; Our results indicate that TMAO levels are decreased by lifestyle intervention in
children with obesity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
